Ashley W. Oughterson collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Ashley W. Oughterson collection
1943-1959
Ms Coll 51
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
The collection includes a small amount of correspondence; a notebook including Oughterson's account of his travel to and first days in Japan in 1945; a form for examining those exposed to the atomic bomb; clippings and articles about Oughterson; obituaries including a lengthy memoir published separately by John F. Fulton and Eugene Davidson; photographs; and articles on military medicine and the atomic and H-bomb collected by Oughterson.
Oughterson, Ashley Webster, 1895-1956
Related Materials
Averill A. Liebow Collection (Ms Coll 28).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ashley Webster Oughterson, known as "Scotty," was born in Seneca, New York on September 28, 1895. A graduate of Harvard Medical School in 1924, after internships in Boston and New York, he served as an assistant resident under Harvey Cushing at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston. He came to Yale in 1928 as the William Harvey Cushing Memorial Fellow in the Department of Surgery, after which he was appointed to the faculty. In 1943, he became a clinical faculty member. Oughterson's wife, Dr. Marion Edith Howard, was a member of the Department of Internal Medicine. During World War II, Oughterson first served with the Yale 39th General Hospital in New Zealand, and was then appointed chief surgical consultant to the American forces in the Pacific under General MacArthur. In 1945 he became Chairman of the Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan. As a clinician and researcher, he focused on the diagnosis of cancer and surgical treatment. In 1946, Oughterson became executive vice-president of the American Cancer Society. After visiting South America in 1955, he persuaded the Rockefeller Foundation to establish a program to aid medical education in Colombia. He was made a consultant to the Rockefeller Foundation and moved with his wife to Cali, Colombia. While in the process of visiting medical centers in Colombia, he died in a plane crash on November 18, 1956. Oughterson co-edited with Shields Warren, Medical Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan (1956). An active member of the Associates of the Yale Medical Library, he collected materials on founding Yale surgeon Nathan Smith for a possible biography.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the first folders 1-5 and 11-17 were found in a mezzanine office of the Historical Library that had been used by Oughterson's widow Dr. Marion Howard. Other materials were added in 2014 from the Library's Obituary Files.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains: a small amount of correspondence; a notebook including Oughterson's account of his travel to and first days in Japan in 1945; forms for examining those exposed to the atomic bomb; clippings and articles about Oughterson; obituaries, including a biography published separately by John F. Fulton and Eugene Davidson; photographs; and articles on military medicine and the atomic and hydrogen bomb collected by Oughterson. Other photographs had previously been transferred to the Library's photograph collection.
Atomic bomb -- Blast effect; Medical education -- Colombia; Medicine, Military; Surgeons -- Connecticut; World War, 1939-1945 -- Health aspects; Diaries; Photographs; Surgeons -- Connecticut; Davidson, Eugene, 1902-2002; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Peter Bent Brigham Hospital; Rockefeller Foundation; United States. Joint Commission for the Investigation of the Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Japan; Yale Medical Library. Historical Library; Yale University. Department of Surgery
- Correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Carbon copies of three letters: Oughterson to Robert Zollinger, Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston, 1946 February 1; James P. Cooney, Atomic Energy Commission, to Oughterson, 1950 March 31; George Baehr, Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, to Oughterson, 1955 June 20. Oughterson supported prepaid medical insurance plans.
- Notebook on travel to and arrival in Japan, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Lined notebook, 15.5 x 10 cm, with pages folded on the bottom that extend to 20.5 cm. The first pages contain a narrative that begins January 3, 1945 with Oughterson's departure from the Unites States and his arrival in Japan. He describes bombs and air raids. Other parts of the notebook, most of which is blank, contain miscellaneous notes. The folder also includes a separate sheet of paper containing references from 1942 to 1947, and a larger sheet on which Oughterson has written, "This is a bone fida gift from a member of the Armed Forces and entitled to free entry."
- Atomic Bomb Joint Commission Investigation form, ca. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Four mimeographed copies of the form to record location, injuries, and symptoms for individuals who were affected by the atomic bomb.
- Yale [Daily] News issue with headline, "Army Air Corps Moves in as 500 Students Move Out", 1943 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  The entire issue is devoted to the war. On the last page is a photograph of the 39th General Hospital and the article "Yale Medical Unit and Nursing School Convert to War."
- Yale [Daily] News issue with an article on Oughterson, 1944 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Issue containing the article, "Col. Oughterson is Given New Post in South Pacific," on page 1.
- Newspaper clippings on Oughterson, 1944-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reviews of Medical Effects of the Atomic Bomb, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Obituaries (Box 1, Folder 8)
  These include John F. Fulton and Eugene Davidson, Ashley Webster Oughterson [New Haven]: Sponsored by the Trustees of the Associates of Yale Medical Library, [no date], plus three other obituaries, and a poem, "Ashley Oughterson," by Eugene Davidson.
- Correspondence of John F. Fulton on Oughterson memoir, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  See Folder 7 for obituaries and Fulton's memoir.
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Two photographs. One unlabeled photograph appears to be the staff of the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston. The second photograph is labeled "Medical School and Hospital Staffs...Cali, Colombia."
- Article by Kenneth W. Thomson, "Dermatomycosis, Ulceration, and Gangrene," with a paragraph inscription to Oughterson, 1945 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  The full title is "Studies on the Relationship of Dermatomycosis to Ulceration and Gangrene of the Extremities," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 16[6] (July 1944): 665-754. Thomson, a member of the Department of Surgery at Yale, writes "This is the legacy you left me," and wishes Oughterson good luck on going to Japan (see folder 2).
- Articles collected by Oughterson on field casualties, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  13 items.
- Articles collected by Oughterson on radiation, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Four items.
- Nuclear Physics for the Medical Officer: Lectures Given to Army Medical Officers at the Army Medical Department Research & Graduate School, Washington, D.C., prepared by R.E. Lapp, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Mimeographed set of lectures, various paginations.
- Bulletin of the U.S. Army Medical Department issue with an article on the atomic bomb, 1948 July (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Scientific American issue with articles on the H-Bomb, 1950 March (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists issue with articles on the atomic bomb and H-bomb, 1950 April (Box 1, Folder 16)